This is Our Home, It Is Not For Sale Film Collection 2010-020
University of Houston Libraries Special Collections
This is Our Home, It Is Not For Sale Film Collection
1925-2011
1985-1988
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Schwartz, Jon, 1948-
2010-020
4.00 Linear Feet
112 Reels
The This is Our Home, It Is Not for Sale Film Collection contains records covering the full scope of the production of a documentary film. Records cover fundraising activities, releases and contracts, insurance, research materials, production notes and logs, film screenings and festivals, photographs, and posters.
Biographical Information:
This is Our Home, It Is Not for Sale is a documentary film produced by Jon Schwartz.
Jon Schwartz grew up in a neighborhood contiguous to Riverside, and produced his three-hour documentary as something of a paean to the beauty and complexity of Riverside as it was and as it evolved. Schwartz earned a degree in film and moved to the West Coast, but he found the inspiration for his film project in a 1983 photography exhibit at the Houston Public Library. Schwartz's research for the film included 300 preliminary interviews plus magazine articles and academic papers on Houston. Schwartz was remarkably successful in raising funds to produce his film, engaging the interest not only of funding organizations but also former and current residents of Riverside.
Schwartz's film traces the history of Houston's Riverside neighborhood from land grant to inner city neighborhood. Boundaries of Riverside are defined in the film as Alabama Street on the north, University of Houston on the east, Old Spanish Trail on the south, and Almeda Road on the west. Schwartz tells the story of Riverside through interviews, photos, and home movies. Informally known as the Jewish River Oaks, Riverside became an idyllic neighborhood close to downtown. Riverside was an all-white neighborhood until 1952 when the first black family moved in; white flight followed. Real estate agents working house-to-house encouraged owners to sell, but many residents resisted the inclination to move and posted yard signs stating "This is Our Home, It's Not for Sale." Transformation became inevitable for a constellation of reasons. Intrusions into the neighborhood included Highway 288 and the Harris County Psychiatric Center. By the conclusion of the time period covered in the film (mid-1980s), Riverside was a multi-ethnic neighborhood, combining characteristics of a peaceful wooded residential area with the conflicts of an integrated urban neighborhood.
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Separated Materials:
This Is Our Home, It Is Not For Sale DVD (http://library.uh.edu/record=b3877445~S11)
Scope and Contents
The This is Our Home, It Is Not for Sale Film Collection contains records covering the full scope of the production of a documentary film. Records cover fundraising activities, releases and contracts, insurance, research materials, production notes and logs, film screenings and festivals, photographs, and posters.
The documentary film is available for viewing on DVD in UH Libraries Special Collections and for purchase at http://thisisourhomeitisnotforsale.com.
Articles; Audiovisual materials; Contract documents; Correspondence; Newspapers; Photographs; Posters; Houston (Tex.) -- Race relations -- History -- 20th Century; Riverside Terrace (Houston, Tex.) -- History -- 20th Century; African Americans -- Segregation -- Texas -- Houston; African Americans -- Texas -- Houston -- Social conditions -- 20th Century; Demographic transition -- Texas -- Houston -- History -- 20th Century; Jews -- Texas -- Houston -- Migrations -- 20th Century; Middle class African Americans -- Texas -- Houston -- History -- 20th Century; Migration, Internal -- Texas -- Houston -- History -- 20th Century; Whites -- Texas -- Houston -- Migrations -- 20th Century
- Film
  - Interviews
    - Margie Abrams, October 17, 1985
    - Tom Bagby, November 14, 1985
    - Shirley Bannerot, November 7, 1985
    - Keith Bardin, November 11, 1985
    - Michelle Barnes, October 11, 1985
    - Cebe Sue Barnett, November 1, 1985
    - Tom Bass, November 1, 1985
    - Weldon H. Berry, November 13, 1985
    - Cherie Bourgin, October 23, 1985
    - Harry Brochstein, October 23, 1985
    - Donald Caesar, November 1, 1985
    - Carman Family, October 17, 1985
    - Carman Family, October 17, 1985
    - Anthony Chase, November 3, 1985
    - John and Drucie Chase, November 3, 1985
    - Arnett Cobb, November 11, 1985
    - Mary Craft and Eugene Smith, October 12, 1985
    - Riva Deutser, November 4, 1985
    - Ray Dickens, November 7, 1985
    - Hortense Dixon, November 13, 1985
    - James Donatto, October 30, 1985
    - James M. Douglas, October 28, 1985
    - Al Edwards, October 25, 1985
    - Edith Eisner, October 23, 1985
    - Stanley Epstein, October 31, 1985
    - Dora Finger, October 16, 1985
    - Eve France, November 1, 1985
    - Clarice Freeman, October 14, 1985
    - Henry Gissel, November 3, 1985
    - Billy B. Goldberg, November 8, 1985
    - Frank Goldberg, October 11, 1985
    - Anthony and Carolyn Hall, July 7, 1986
    - Mack H. Hannah, Jr., November 14, 1985
    - Gaylen Harris and Bill Bardwell, October 13, 1985
    - Lullelia Harrison, October 11, 1985
    - Jack Heard, Sr., November 4, 1985
    - Donald Hill, October 12, 1985
    - Holly Hogrobrooks and Otis King, October 27, 1988
    - Wally Honeywell, October 25, 1985
    - Katherine Howe, November 9, 1985
    - Sammye Hughes, October 13, 1985
    - Loraine D. Hunsaker, November 6, 1985
    - Robert Johnson, November 14, 1985
    - Rubye M. Johnson, November 1, 1985
    - J. B. Jones, October 18, 1985
    - J. B. Jones, October 18, 1985
    - Kahn Brothers, October 16-November 13, 1985
    - Kahn Brothers, Mary Jane Thompson
    - Robert I. Kahn, November 13, 1985
    - Walter W. Kemmerer, October 26, 1985
    - Fredell Lack-Eichhorn, November 3, 1985
    - Audrey and William Lawson, May 8, 1987
    - Elwyn Lee and Sheila Jackson Lee, October 21, 1985
    - Elwyn Lee and Sheila Jackson Lee, October 21, 1985
    - L. Thain Leonard, November 7, 1985
    - Jon Lindsay, October 23, 1985
    - Milton Littell, July 8, 1986
    - Edward and Elouise Loonam, October 20, 1985
    - Mary Lou Mailman, October 12, 1985
    - C. M. Malone, Jr., November 14, 1985
    - George A. Martin, November 22, 1987
    - Jim McConn and Johnny Goyen Archer, November 8, 1985
    - George McElroy, October 26, 1985
    - John M. McGinty, November 1, 1985
    - Quentin R. Mease, October 30, 1985
    - Manning M. Mott, October 28, 1985
    - J. C. Nickens, November 9, 1985
    - Gregg and Anita O'Neil, October 30, 1985
    - Faurice Edwin Prince and Jessie Lee Prince, November 11, 1985
    - Bitsy Proler, November 10, 1985
    - Nat Pryzant, October 19, 1985
    - Dan Pulaski, November 10, 1985
    - Frances Rich, October 31, 1985
    - Frances Rich, October 31, 1985
    - Drew Robins, October 27, 1985
    - Joe Russell, October 21, 1985
    - Ann Sakowitz, July 7, 1986
    - Robert Sakowitz, November 9, 1985
    - Joseph Samuels, October 17, 1985
    - Joseph Samuels, October 17, 1985
    - Hyman Schachtel, July 7, 1986
    - Lionel M. Schooler, October 19, 1985
    - Jane S. Self, July 8, 1986
    - Jack Shannon, October 24, 1985
    - Sidney and Mary Smiley, October 16, 1985
    - Sidney Smiley, October 16, 1985
    - P. B. Smith, October 12, 1985
    - Andrew C. Sorelle, Jr., November 4, 1985
    - Leonard H. O. Spearman, October 30, 1985
    - Macy Stern, October 13, 1985
    - Harry Taylor, October 14, 1985
    - Martha Terrill, October 27, 1985
    - Robert J. and Mercedes Terry, October 18, 1985
    - Evelyn B. and Peter Thornton, October 24-26, 1985
    - Toby Topek, October 11, 1985
    - James Tucker and Michael Tucker, July 7, 1986
    - James L. Tucker, July 7, 1986
    - Clen Del Vance, Sr., October 20, 1985
    - Anna and J. S. Waldman, October 27, 1985
    - George Washington, Jr., November 11, 1985
    - Sol B. Weiner, October 30, 1985
    - Jack Weingarten, November 8, 1985
    - Malvina Weingarten, November 3, 1985
    - David Westheimer, October 14, 1986
    - Bettye White, November 11, 1985
    - Hattie Mae White, November 10, 1985
    - Thomas D. White, November 14, 1985
    - Stewart and Rhona Ryan Wilber, October 26, 1985
    - Avrohm Wisenberg, October 31, 1985
    - Alvin Zimmerman, November 3, 1985
    - Marvin Zindler, October 25, 1985
    - Pickup Interviews
  - Additional Film Elements
- Funding and Expenses
  - Southwest Alternative Media Project (SWAMP), 1977-1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Grant Proposal #1, 1981-1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Grant Proposal #2, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lab and Equipment Information (Continental), 1982-1989 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Texas Committee for the Humanities (3rd Proposal), 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Production File, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Fundraiser, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Legal
  - Signed Releases, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Personnel and Contracts, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Insurance, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Research
  - Guardian Trust (photo and correspondence), 1925 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Sources, 1925-1976 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Sources, 1981-2010 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Jewish Herald-Voice, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper Article about Riverside, 1953-1995 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
  - Civic Clubs, 1958-1985 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Preliminary Interview Notes on Index Cards, undated (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
- Production
  - Director's Notes, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Director's Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Cinesound Logs, undated (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - Dub Log, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Editing Code Log, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Film Roll Log, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Interview Code Log, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Film Festivals and Awards
  - Houston/Harris County Sesquicentennial Committee, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Chicago Film Festival, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Telluride Film Festival, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Edinburgh Film Festival, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Film Festivals #1, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Anthropos Film Festival, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Denver Film Festival, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Hawaii Film Festival, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Houston Film Festival, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Robert Flaherty Seminar, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - San Francisco Film Festival, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Film Festivals #2 (post-film festival screenings), 1988-2008 (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
  - Joseph Papp Documentary Festival, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Screening and Press Coverage
  - Correspondence, 1983-2008 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Reviews and Press Articles, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Reviews and Press Articles, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Critiques and Press Releases, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Houston Screenings (with photo), 1987-2005 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Distribution, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Distribution, 1988-1995 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Photos, Still Slides, and Captions
  - Almeda Photos, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Bob Bailey Studios Inc. Prints, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Houston Chronicle Photo Prints, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Photo Captions, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Photo Prints with Captions, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Proof Sheets with Negatives, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Still Photo Credits, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Oversize Material
  - Newspaper Posters, 1953-1964 (Ovs box 4, Item 1)
  - Tract Maps and Property Information (Sanborne map and homeowner info), 1984 (Ovs box 4, Item 2)
  - Chicago International Film Festival Award, 1987 (Ovs box 4, Item 3)
  - Houston International Film Festival Award, 1988 (Ovs box 4, Item 4)
  - Newell Color Lab 11x14" B/W Print, undated (Ovs box 4, Item 5)
  - Magazines about zoning, Spring 2011 (Ovs box 4, Item 6)
  - Newspapers and Articles, 1925-2010 (Ovs box 4, Item 7)